JOOYOUNG SEO: Hello.
I'm JooYoung Seo, a doctoral student
in learning design technology
program at Penn State.
And I was one of the
interns at RStudio in 2020.
I've been using R without
sight because I'm blind.
Yeah, I understand that you
might have a big question
mark in mind--
how a blind person could do data
science or even use a computer?
In this talk, I'll answer
the fundamental questions
that you might have by
demonstrating some strategies
that I've used plus by
introducing some accessibility
improvements made
from RStudio IDE
and Shiny that I was
involved in for my internship.
OK, let's get started.
If we're talking about
R and data science,
let me address this
question first.
How do I use a computer?
Well, I need to ask you back.
Then how do you
use your computer?
In other words, how do you
interact with computer?
We could break down the way
we interact with computer
into input and output--
that is, how we pass
information to computer
and how we get
information from computer.
What if we would remove
visual aspect from the two
modes of interactions?
Undoubtedly, using mouse
would become almost impossible
or even useless.
I doubt no one could
point and double
click RStudio icon on their
desktop in a stable fashion
when blindfolded.
But you can still use keyboard
as long as your muscle memory
remembers your keyboard layout.
What about output?
We need some workarounds
alternative to visual monitor,
like using sound output instead.
I use computer via keyboard
only input and sound and tactile
output just like this.
SPEAKER 1: [INAUDIBLE]
JOOYOUNG SEO: Isn't
it too fast for you?
No worries.
Let me slow it down for you.
SPEAKER 1: Slower, slower,
slower, slower, slower, slower,
slower, slower,
slower, slower, slower.
[INAUDIBLE] left
[INAUDIBLE] right Enter.
One, hello world
greater [INAUDIBLE].
R graphics, device two active.
JOOYOUNG SEO: Now that you got
how I interact with computer,
let's talk about data science.
Data science involves a
cycle interaction with data,
such as importing, tidying,
transforming, visualizing,
and modeling.
And it feels like data science
is highly vision-dominant.
Yes, it could be.
But data science is
more than what is seen.
If data science was restricted
to only vision domain,
that would mean that people who
cannot employ vision science
can't do data science at all.
Very fortunately,
however, that is not true
because we have R, which
enables blind people see data
beyond visual models
I believe R is one of the most
accessible data environments
because of the
following benefits.
First, command line interface--
as opposed to point and click
graphical user interface which
requires mouse
input interaction,
R is a command line environment.
This means that you can do
everything within terminal
using keyboard only.
This is a good benefit for
keyboard users like me.
Second, the beautiful interplay
between reproducibility
and accessibility--
R Markdown is a
plain text-based document
for reproducible report that can
be written with any text editor
and can be rendered
into multiple formats,
including HTML, Word,
PDF, epub, and more.
These outputs in many cases
are made readily accessible
to assisted technologies,
especially the HTML output
is super accessible.
Last but not least, there are
a number of accessible packages
out there thanks to
its open source nature.
There are two either
accessible or semi-accessible
integrated development
environments
supporting R programming.
One is RStudio IDE
version 1.3 or later.
The other one is
Visual Studio code
with some extensions for
R. It was such an honor
for me to be part of the
RStudio accessibility
project for my summer
2020 internship
under the great double
mentorship of Gary
Richie on RStudio team and
Winston Chang on Shiny
team.
Since RStudio has just started
its accessibility support,
there are still rooms
for further improvements,
but we can at least
recommend trying out
RStudio Server for keyboard
or screen reader users
to benefit from its
accessibility enhancements.
As RStudio Server
requires Linux system,
Windows users need
virtual technology called
Windows subsystem for Linux.
And we published the
technical details for this.
Just check it out.
Here are some accessibility
options currently supported
in RStudio server
version 1.3 or higher.
We have added screen reader
support, animation reduction,
tab key focus
control, et cetera.
And previously, it was very
challenging for keyboard users
to move their focus around.
But now, you can get
your focus moved around
by pressing Tab key from
menu bar all the way down
to workbench area.
You can send any inquiries
or suggestions directly
to accessibility@rstudio.com.
Now it's time to introduce
some accessible and useful R
packages that I've used.
I use gt when
interacting with data
frame and other tidy data
table, and I use sonify
for two dimensional
scatterplot or line charts.
BrailleR package is very useful
for understanding histogram,
bar plot, and box plot.
Shiny-- it used to be
not very accessible,
but it's getting accessible.
So of course, I use it for
interactive data science work.
RMarkdown is such an
accessible Swiss army knife
because you can do almost
everything possible in R
and turn it into
accessible output.
All right, let me walk
you through each of them
from how I interact
with data frame.
I assume View() is one of the
most widely used basic functions
among R users to get a better
sense of data frame structure.
Unfortunately, the
default Data Viewer
called from utils package
is completely inaccessible.
This means that screen reader
does not read anything for you
from the default pane.
RStudio has replaced
this default one
with their enhanced data
viewer, which is accessible.
However, that's not
a universal solution
for those who do
not use RStudio IDE.
My simple go-to is gt,
developed by Rich and Joe.
gt stands for Grammar
of Tables, and it
has a number of good
features that helps
you create nice-looking tables.
But I use its core function,
gt::gt(), in lieu of data viewer.
Why I use this?
Because it
generates and opens
an HTML table which is fully
screen reader accessible
and keyboard users.
Next I will talk about how I
interpret a two dimensional
scatterplot.
On the left hand side, we
have a simple scatterplot
with x and y-axes.
How would you be
able to represent
this visualization in a way that
blind people could also digest?
What about using sound?
Say, for example, we
can represent values
on x-axis using stereo panning
sound from left to right.
And we could map y-axis
values with different pitch.
Data points that are higher on
the graph have a higher pitch.
Data points that are
lower on the graph
have corresponding lower pitch.
Just take a listen.
It makes sense, doesn't it?
This technique that
represents data using sound
is called sonification.
I used data
sonification alternative
to data visualization.
We can also try this out with
sonified package developed
by Stefan Siegert
and Robin Williams.
Next, I will show you how
I interact with histogram.
Here is a visual histogram.
How could we make it accessible
to people who are blind?
Yes, of course, we can use
data sonification again
by mapping x and
y-axes it sounds.
But I would like to
introduce another way of data
representation this time.
That is using text description.
The BrailleR package
developed by Jonathan Godfrey
has a function that
translates some R
graphs into alternative
textual description.
You can call this
function by VI(), which
stands for Vision Impairments.
This package is currently
available on GitHub that you
can install via
remotes::install_github()
function.
For box plot interaction,
we can apply the same method
to this visualization
just like this.
I know we got a quite long
description this time,
but it's cool that we can
have auto generated alt
text for some basic R graphs.
If you are an R
developer, please
help Jonathan
Godfrey on GitHub
to support more types of graphs.
OK, I want to turn into
accessible math content
interaction.
I kept mentioning that RMarkdown
contributes to accessibility.
One of the most pleasant
supports is accessible math.
For HTML output, RMarkdown
uses mathjax
JS library by default for
LaTex math expressions,
and this is rendered into
accessible math markup language
content that is fully accessible
with modern screen readers.
I'm going to talk a
little bit about shiny.
I'm super excited to
announce that shiny
is getting accessible.
With the amazing support of
Winston, Carson, Barrett,
and other Shiny
team members, I was
working for making Shiny
accessible for my internship
activity at RStudio.
As a result, you will see many
accessibility improvements
in the next shiny release
version 1.6 or higher.
If you want to test the
development version,
that's available on GitHub,
and you can install it
through remotes package.
Some significant
improvements are as follows.
First, we've added Paypal's
bootstrap accessibility plug-in
under the hood.
So alert, tooltip, pop over,
modal dialog, dropdown,
tab panel, collapse,
and carrousel elements
are made keyboard-accessible.
Next, there are many
significant improvements
made for Shiny widgets.
Select input, especially
sanitize input,
file input, are now fully
keyboard accessible.
Font awesome and glyphy icon
now produces appropriate labels
based on icon names
for screen readers.
Radio buttons and
chatbox query input
are appropriately
grouped together
for assistive technologies.
Date input and date range
input are properly labeled.
And now dynamic content within
all of the output and updated
input are auto-announced to
screen readers and refreshable
for a display.
There are also some
great enhancements
for semantic accessibility.
We can pass alt text
to render plot function
to specify alternative text
description for screen readers.
It could be a static text.
Plot object is given by
default, or you can even
use reactive function
for alt term
to create dynamic
text that is useful
when you want to create
reactive alt text in response
to user input.
And you can explicitly set
the lang code, the language code,
used within your shiny app
by passing lang parameter
to full page function.
This helps search engine
parsers and assistive tech
that are identified
document language.
Last but not least,
semantic landmarks
have been applied to main
panel as well as sidebar panel
for screen readers
to quickly navigate
through Shiny apps
in a logical manner.
It's time to close my talk.
I have touched upon some
fundamental questions
that you might have.
How could a blind
person do computer,
and how could a blind
person do data science?
As my presentation
title suggests,
we can make data science
accessible beyond visual models
because data science
requires insight, not sight.
And all is possible with R.
According to the World Health
Organization's 2018 report,
globally, more than
1.3 billion people
have some varying degree
of visual impairments
and 36 million of
whom are blind.
I'm just one of them.
Why not we invite more people
with diverse abilities to use R
and to enjoy data sciencing?
Thank you.