MAYA GANS: Hi.
My name is Maya Gans.
And in this talk,
I want to tell you
how to start your own
virtual book club.
So this idea came to me in
the beginning of lockdown.
I found myself
feeling really alone.
And also, scrolling
through Twitter,
I saw everyone taking on
these new, exciting hobbies.
Like remember the time
when there were so many
pictures of sourdough?
So I was looking
at my bookshelf.
And I saw Advanced
R. And I realized
that I use as a reference but
I never read it cover to cover.
So I wanted to use the lockdown
opportunity to do that.
And I found myself
asking a lot of questions
that I didn't have
the answers to.
So I reached out to Jon Harmon,
the moderator of the R for Data
Science Slack channel.
And he allowed me
to start a book club
channel within that Slack
and to just see what happens.
And the results were magical.
12 of us ended up meeting weekly
for the entirety of the book
so I think over the
course of 25 weeks.
And we went from essentially
a group of strangers
to now a group of
really good friends.
So first, I want to talk
about the cornerstones of why
I think that this worked.
And the reasons are twofold.
We created a microcosm within
an already existing community.
So you might say there's already
R Ladies or other chapters
and groups out there.
And that's true.
But that's thousands of
faceless group members
who albeit are extremely
helpful and inviting
whereas this group was 12 of us
meeting on Zoom with the camera
on and really
humanizing this learning
experience with each other.
The other component was that
we made this as asynchronous
compatible as possible.
So each meeting was
recorded and put on YouTube.
So if you couldn't attend,
you can watch that.
But we also had this
slack channel for people
to ask questions and even answer
them whenever they get to them.
So you weren't really
limited and locked down
to this single hour.
Now, the meetings themselves
changed over time,
what we did with them.
In the beginning, we took
the first 30 or so minutes
to review what we
found in the chapter
and then used the rest of
the time to answer questions.
But after a couple weeks,
maybe around week eight
or so, I was getting kind
of bored with this model.
And I wanted to
make an application.
I made a Shiny app that uses
the concepts within a chapter.
And granted, the Shiny app was
super buggy, didn't even work.
But within the hour, we
all debugged it together
and got it up and running.
And I think that was kind of
a paradigm shift where people
started, rather than just
relaying information,
they showed us their
packages or other creations.
And it was incredibly
inspiring and eye
opening to see how people are
using these fundamentals just
in these chapters.
So now let's get
to the secret sauce
of why I think this
model worked, right?
We're not the first people
to make a book club.
And I think it's
because of two things.
One is that we
have a facilitator
for each of our books.
And in this case, it was me who
granted I'm pretty extroverted.
And I was totally fine
pinging people on Slack
and being like, hey,
it's Thursday night.
time to meet.
But you don't have
to be that pushy.
Rather, the point
of the facilitator
is that every week
there is an agenda.
And if no one is able to
give that presentation
for that week, then the
onus is on the presenter
to take that upon themselves.
Or else the book might
falter to the wayside.
The other component is
collaborative infrastructure.
And for our case, we used GitHub.
And this image as well as the
text before this are links.
So feel free to go
out to our GitHub.
But our GitHub
has three folders.
The first is our presentations
so the actual Markdown
presentations from each week.
The second folder contains a
breakdown of all the questions
and answers collated
from the Slack channel
so that you don't have
to sift through that.
And the last folder
is a data folder.
And in this folder, we took
that concept of applications
and took a data set and drilled
down into it where each chapter
we applied that to this
data set of our own.
Now to talk about side dishes.
So when we started this
book club, at the outset,
the goal was essentially learn
the contents of the chapters.
But we ended up learning all of
these external things as well.
So I personally
onboarded people onto how
to use GitHub in a
collaborative sense
and collaborate on
a single project.
We also learned a lot about
R Markdown, HTML, and CSS.
And lastly, and maybe
even most importantly,
we were still leveling up
on our presentation skills
in these times where we're
all isolated and alone.
So I want to leave you now
with a recipe card essentially
to recreate this recipe
that worked for us.
And the recipe here is kind of I
break it down into seven steps.
The first is pick a book.
What book do you want to learn?
The second is find
an online community
to make this as
asynchronous as possible.
The third is to blast
it on social media.
The fourth is some books
have natural breaks that
might not be the chapters.
So you might chop
them into segments
that are logical breaks, and
then take a pulse on the group
and on yourself and
see what's working
in that that precious hour
that you're meeting together.
And don't be afraid
to switch it up.
Then lastly, I think it was
really awesome and fun that we
utilized applications
of the chapter
rather than just
keeping it theoretical.
And of course, in
the end, have fun.
So there's a link to the Slack
channel here because I would
really like if you are going to
create a book club to just let
us know what works
and what didn't.
And thank you so much for
listening to this talk.